<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>2016-2018 Sessional Lecturer Handbook</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>TEI-XML Edition</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>University of Lethbridge Faculty Association (ULFA)</authority>
            <date when="2018-04-18"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted by Dan O'Donnell from the official Word document supplied by Derrick Antson</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the 2018 negotiations</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>All numbered sections converted to TEI:list/item; Objectives and Preamble encoded as
               Paragraphs</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <appInfo>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2018-04-18T00:47:34Z</date>
               <name>O'Donnell</name>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item xml:id="s-d1e37" ana="prologue">
               <hi rend="bold">OBJECTIVES</hi>
               <list>
                  <item xml:id="s-d1e40">The main objectives of this Handbook are the
                     specification of principles and procedures that reflect procedural fairness for
                     the appointment of Sessional Lecturers, the peaceful settlement of all
                     disputes, misunderstandings and grievances and the promotion of harmonious
                     relations between the Board and the Association with respect to Sessional
                     Lecturers.</item>
                  <item xml:id="s-d1e42">The Board and the Association acknowledge:<list type="unordered">
                        <item xml:id="s-d1e45">their joint responsibility for the reasonable
                           and just execution of the terms of this Handbook, and</item>
                        <item xml:id="s-d1e47">subject to the provisions of the Post-Secondary
                           Learning Act and all applicable provincial and federal statutes, as
                           amended from time to time, this Handbook is binding on the Association,
                           the Sessional Lecturers and the Board.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item xml:id="s-d1e49">Toward that end, any invocation of Article <ref target="#s-d1e54">1</ref> or Article <ref target="#s-d1e547">14</ref>
                     regarding a Handbook procedure in progress shall stay the procedure pending a
                     resolution of the interpretation or grievance.</item>
                  <item xml:id="s-d1e51">Any deadlines mentioned in this agreement may be
                     varied by written mutual consent prior to the deadline, by the Board and the
                     Association and by the Sessional Lecturer in cases where the deadline affects
                     the Sessional Lecturer concerned.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list>
            <item n="1" xml:id="s-d1e54">
               <hi rend="bold">Interpretation of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="1.01" xml:id="s-d1e64">Any item or provision inadvertently omitted or
                     found to be missing in this Handbook, shall be referred to either the President
                     of the University or the President of the Association. Only the President of
                     the University or the President of the Association may choose to convene the
                     Interpretation Committee as in Article <ref target="#s-d1e70">1.04</ref>. The
                     Interpretation Committee shall resolve uncertainties caused by the
                     omitted/missing item or provision.</item>
                  <item n="1.02" xml:id="s-d1e66">Uncertainties or disagreements about the meaning
                     of the Articles of this Handbook shall be referred to either the President of
                     the University or the President of the Association. Only the President of the
                     University or the President of the Association may choose to convene the
                     Interpretation Committee as in Article <ref target="#s-d1e70">1.04</ref>.
                     The Interpretation Committee shall resolve uncertainties or disagreements about
                     the meaning of the Articles of this Handbook.</item>
                  <item n="1.03" xml:id="s-d1e68">The Interpretation Committee shall consist of the
                     President of the University and the President of the Association.</item>
                  <item n="1.04" xml:id="s-d1e70">The Interpretation Committee shall meet within
                     five (5) working days of the written request of either of its members.</item>
                  <item n="1.05" xml:id="item_xhy_h15_pdb"/>
                  <item n="1.06" xml:id="s-d1e65">Where the Interpretation Committee agrees upon an
                     interpretation, it shall become a Schedule of this Handbook until it is
                     incorporated by amendment of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook pursuant to
                     Article <ref target="#s-d1e153">3</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="1.07" xml:id="s-d1e79">Where the Interpretation Committee cannot agree
                     upon an interpretation within five (5) working days of the meeting of Article
                        <ref target="#s-d1e70">1.04</ref>, each member shall set forth an
                     interpretation in writing, and the two interpretations shall be submitted to an
                     arbitrator jointly selected by them. If an Interpretation Committee cannot
                     agree on the selection of an arbitrator within five (5) working days after the
                     meeting of Article <ref target="#s-d1e70">1.04</ref>, the arbitrator shall be
                     appointed by a Judge of the Alberta Court of Queen's Bench upon the Petition of
                     either party. </item>
                  <item n="1.08" xml:id="s-d1e81">The arbitrator shall meet only with both
                     Presidents and only jointly, unless the Presidents agree otherwise in writing.
                     Both Presidents shall make a reasonable effort to cooperate with the
                     arbitrator's investigation.</item>
                  <item n="1.09" xml:id="s-d1e83">The arbitrator shall first attempt to mediate the
                     dispute. If the attempt to mediate fails, the arbitrator shall within twenty
                     (20) working days of his/her appointment select without alteration either the
                     Board’s or the Association’s interpretation. The arbitrator's decision shall be
                     final and binding on the Board, the Association, and the Interpretation
                     Committee.</item>
                  <item n="1.10" xml:id="s-d1e87"> The arbitrator's decision shall become a schedule
                     of this Handbook, until it is incorporated by amendment of the Sessional
                     Lecturers Handbook pursuant to Article <ref target="#s-d1e153">3</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="1.11" xml:id="s-d1e91">Any interpretation pursuant to Article <ref target="#s-d1e65">1.06</ref> or Article <ref target="#s-d1e65">1.06</ref>
                     shall be made known in writing by the President of the University to persons
                     affected by it.</item>
                  <item n="1.12" xml:id="s-d1e93">The costs of arbitration shall be shared by the
                     Board and the Association.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="2" xml:id="s-d1e80">
               <hi rend="bold">Definitions</hi>
               <p>In this Handbook:</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="2.01" xml:id="s-d1e102">"Academic Assistant" shall mean a member of the
                     academic staff holding an appointment with the rank of Academic Assistant. </item>
                  <item n="2.02" xml:id="s-d1e104">"Academic Staff Member/Academic Staff" shall mean
                     an individual University employee or a category of University employees
                     designated by the Board as Academic Staff. </item>
                  <item n="2.03" xml:id="s-d1e106">"Association" shall mean The University of
                     Lethbridge Faculty Association. </item>
                  <item n="2.04" xml:id="s-d1e108">"Board" shall mean the Board of Governors of The
                     University of Lethbridge. </item>
                  <item n="2.05" xml:id="s-d1e110">"Dean" shall mean the Dean of a Faculty/School or
                     a person authorized to act in that capacity. </item>
                  <item n="2.06" xml:id="s-d1e112">"Department" shall mean an academic unit
                     established by the Board under that designation. </item>
                  <item n="2.07" xml:id="s-d1e114">"Department Chair" shall mean a person authorized
                     to act in that capacity. </item>
                  <item n="2.08" xml:id="s-d1e116">"Dean of School" shall mean a person authorized
                     to act in that capacity. </item>
                  <item n="2.09" xml:id="s-d1e118">"Faculty" shall mean an academic unit established
                     by the Board under that designation.</item>
                  <item n="2.10" xml:id="s-d1e120">"Faculty Member" shall mean a member of the
                     academic staff with the rank of Professor, Associate Professor, Assistant
                     Professor or Lecturer. </item>
                  <item n="2.11" xml:id="s-d1e122">"Faculty Member” shall mean a member of the
                     academic staff with the rank of Professor, Associate Professor, or Assistant
                     Professor.</item>
                  <item n="2.12" xml:id="s-d1e125">“Instructor” shall mean an employee of the
                     academic staff holding an appointment with the rank of Instructor</item>
                  <item n="2.13" xml:id="s-d1e127">“Instructor/Academic Assistant” shall mean
                     Instructor(s) or Academic Assistant(s).</item>
                  <item n="2.14" xml:id="s-d1e129">"Member" shall mean an employee of the Board who
                     is a Sessional Lecturer. </item>
                  <item n="2.15" xml:id="s-d1e131">"Parties" shall mean the Board and the
                     Association. </item>
                  <item n="2.16" xml:id="s-d1e119">"Personal file" shall mean the file maintained by
                     the Dean pertaining to a Member and which contains materials subject to Article
                        <ref target="#s-d1e279">8</ref> of this Handbook.</item>
                  <item n="2.17" xml:id="s-d1e137">"Post-retirement contract" shall mean an
                     employment contract that has been negotiated between a retired Faculty Member
                     and the Board made at the discretion of the Board not including contracts for a
                     Sessional Lecturer. </item>
                  <item n="2.18" xml:id="s-d1e139">"President" shall mean the President of the
                     University, or a person authorized to act in that capacity.</item>
                  <item n="2.19" xml:id="s-d1e141">"Procedural fairness" shall mean <list>
                        <item n="2.19.1" xml:id="s-d1e144">the duty to make a decision without a
                           reasonable apprehension of bias or a conflict of interest. Prior
                           familiarity with the facts of a case does not, by itself, constitute a
                           reasonable apprehension of bias, nor do past friendly or unfriendly
                           relationships. AND</item>
                        <item n="2.19.2" xml:id="s-d1e146">the duty of an adjudicator to interpret
                           and apply the Sessional Lecturers Handbook, in a reasonable manner. A
                           disagreement with a decision or judgment does not, in itself, constitute
                           a misinterpretation or misapplication of the Sessional Lecturers
                           Handbook, nor does it constitute an unreasonable interpretation or
                           application of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook. AND </item>
                        <item n="2.19.3" xml:id="s-d1e148">the adjudicator or adjudicators shall,
                           within reason, ensure that adequate evidence is presented or collected to
                           meet the standard of proof appropriate to support the decision and shall
                           give due consideration to such evidence. AND </item>
                        <item n="2.19.4" xml:id="s-d1e150">the parties to the procedure have a right
                           to know all the relevant evidence presented in the decision making
                           process. AND </item>
                        <item n="2.19.5" xml:id="s-d1e152">the parties to the procedure have an
                           opportunity to respond to all relevant evidence presented in the decision
                           making process. AND </item>
                        <item n="2.19.6" xml:id="s-d1e154">the parties to the procedure have a
                           reasonable opportunity to present their case to the adjudicator or
                           adjudicators.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2.20" xml:id="s-d1e156">"School" shall mean an academic unit established
                     by the Board under that designation. </item>
                  <item n="2.21" xml:id="s-d1e158">"Senior Academic Administrator" shall mean Deans
                     and Associate Deans, Dean, Vice-President (Academic) and Associate
                     Vice-President (Academic), Associate Vice-President (Research), Vice-President
                     (Administration) and Associate Vice-President (Administration), and President,
                     or a person authorized to act in that capacity.</item>
                  <item n="2.22" xml:id="s-d1e160">"Sessional Lecturer" shall mean a member of the
                     Academic Staff appointed by the Dean of a Faculty/Dean of a School to teach no
                     more than one semester course in a designated semester. Normally, the Sessional
                     Lecturer has full responsibility for the course, but on occasion a Sessional
                     Lecturer will be a member appointed at a partial stipend to teach a defined
                     portion of a course with corresponding teaching responsibilities. </item>
                  <item n="2.23" xml:id="s-d1e162">"Sessional Lecturers Handbook" shall mean the
                     Handbook pertaining to Sessional Lecturers, including schedules thereto. The
                     edition of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook in effect is the one most recently
                     ratified by the Board and the Association, including schedules and any
                     interpretations. </item>
                  <item n="2.24" xml:id="s-d1e164">"University" shall mean The University of
                     Lethbridge.</item>
                  <item n="2.25" xml:id="s-d1e166">"Vice-President (Academic)" shall mean the
                     Vice-President (Academic) of the University, or a person authorized to act in
                     that capacity.</item>
                  <item n="2.26" xml:id="s-d1e168">"Working days" shall mean Monday through Friday
                     except holidays as identified within the most current edition of the University
                     of Lethbridge Calendar. </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="3" xml:id="s-d1e153">
               <hi rend="bold">Amendments</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="3.01" xml:id="s-d1e178">This Sessional Lecturers Handbook shall be the
                     only Sessional Lecturers Handbook in effect. It shall continue in force, except
                     as amended through mutual agreement between the parties. </item>
                  <item n="3.02" xml:id="s-d1e180">Negotiation of amendments shall normally occur in
                     the final year of this agreement according to the following schedule: <list>
                        <item n="3.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e163">September 15 to December 15 - A
                           preliminary meeting to review possible issues </item>
                        <item n="3.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e165">February 1 to April 30 - Negotiation by
                           negotiating committees </item>
                        <item n="3.02.3" xml:id="s-d1e167">May 1 to June 30 - Action by both parties
                           respecting negotiated amendments </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3.03" xml:id="s-d1e189">To consider the proposed amendments, each party
                     shall designate a negotiating committee of three persons. The two committees
                     shall meet to negotiate the proposed amendments. </item>
                  <item n="3.04" xml:id="s-d1e191">If the parties agree upon an amendment of this
                     Handbook, the agreement shall include a specification of the date upon which
                     the amendment takes effect, and the amendment shall thereafter become part of
                     this Handbook. </item>
                  <item n="3.05" xml:id="s-d1e193">If the parties cannot agree upon amendment of
                     Schedules A and/or B of this Handbook, the matter shall be referred to
                     arbitration (see Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e837">B</ref>). </item>
                  <item n="3.06" xml:id="s-d1e195">In the event that any provision of this Handbook
                     is found by a court or tribunal of competent jurisdiction to be illegal or
                     unenforceable, then such provision shall be severed from the Sessional
                     Lecturers Handbook as having no force or effect; but the remainder of the
                     Sessional Lecturers Handbook shall continue in full force and effect. In the
                     event any such decision of a court or tribunal of competent jurisdiction is
                     appealed, the operation of the provision in question shall be suspended pending
                     the outcome of such appeal. </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="4" xml:id="s-d1e177">
               <hi rend="bold">Applications and Exclusions</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="4.01" xml:id="s-d1e203">The provisions of this Handbook shall apply to
                     all Sessional Lecturers. </item>
                  <item n="4.02" xml:id="s-d1e205">An individual who intends to remain under an
                     existing employment contract when applying for a Sessional Lecturer position at
                     the University will ensure that he/she can commit to fulfilling the
                     responsibilities of a Sessional Lecturer and will provide evidence that he/she
                     is in a position to make such a commitment. This may involve, but need not be
                     limited to, provision of evidence that his/her employer is aware of their
                     intended Sessional Lecturer commitment and that this commitment will not
                     conflict his/her existing employment contract. </item>
                  <item n="4.03" xml:id="s-d1e207">A retired Faculty Member who has been offered a
                     Sessional Lecturer position at the University must choose between entering into
                     a post-retirement contract or becoming a member under the Sessional Lecturers
                     Handbook.</item>
                  <item n="4.04" xml:id="s-d1e209">The terms of this agreement do not extend to the
                     appointment of: <list>
                        <item n="4.04.1" xml:id="s-d1e212">A continuing Faculty Member who contracts
                           to teach a one semester course on an overload basis. </item>
                        <item n="4.04.2" xml:id="s-d1e214">A retired Faculty Member who teaches part
                           of a one semester course under the terms of a post-retirement contract. </item>
                        <item n="4.04.3" xml:id="s-d1e216">A graduate student who teaches part of a
                           one semester course as part of their assigned and agreed to Teaching
                           Assistant activities. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="5" xml:id="s-d1e196">
               <hi rend="bold">Recognition</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="5.01" xml:id="s-d1e224">The Board recognizes the Association as the
                     exclusive bargaining agent for all Sessional Lecturers. </item>
                  <item n="5.02" xml:id="s-d1e226">The Board shall deduct from the monthly salaries
                     of all Sessional Lecturers dues as assessed by the Association. Dues shall be
                     remitted to the Association, the Confederation of Alberta Faculty Associations
                     (CAFA) and Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) by the last
                     banking day of each month. Any adjustments shall be reconciled in the next
                     month. </item>
                  <item n="5.03" xml:id="s-d1e228">The Board shall inform the Association of the
                     name of and the deductions made for each Sessional Lecturer, and may provide
                     CAUT or CAFA with the following information: <list>
                        <item n="5.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e233">Number of Sessional Lecturers </item>
                        <item n="5.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e235">Total amount being remitted for Sessional
                           Lecturers </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="6" xml:id="s-d1e211">
               <hi rend="bold">Communication and Information</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="6.01" xml:id="s-d1e243">
                     <hi rend="bold">Communication</hi>
                     <p>Unless otherwise provided in this Handbook, all communications or notices
                        concerning or required by the Handbook shall be addressed as follows:</p>
                     <list>
                        <item n="6.01.1" xml:id="f-d1e243"> By the University - To the President,
                           The University of Lethbridge Faculty Association</item>
                        <item n="6.01.2" xml:id="f-d1e245">By the Association - To the President,
                           The University of Lethbridge </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6.02" xml:id="s-d1e256">
                     <hi>Distributing the Sessional Lecturers Handbook</hi>
                     <p>The Board shall put the Handbook on the University website for all Members
                        to access.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6.03" xml:id="s-d1e261">
                     <hi>Information about Sessional Lecturers</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="6.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e266">The Board agrees to provide the
                           Association with specified information for its use in achieving the
                           objectives of this Handbook. The Board shall provide the Association with
                           the following information, in electronic format, for Sessional Lecturers:<list>
                              <item n="6.03.1.A" xml:id="s-d1e269">A list containing name,
                                 faculty/department and campus; this information to be complete as
                                 of September 30 and January 30 and provided to the Association no
                                 later than October 31 and February 28 of each year. </item>
                              <item n="6.03.1.B" xml:id="s-d1e271">A list containing salary, dues,
                                 gender, age as of June 30, and semester of appointment with the
                                 identity of individuals on this list encrypted to ensure privacy of
                                 information; this information to be complete as of September 30 and
                                 January 30 and provided to the Association no later than October 31
                                 and February 28 of each semester.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="6.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e273">The Association agrees to respect the
                           confidentiality of personal information and the privacy of individuals
                           and undertakes that information provided pursuant to this Article shall
                           not be published or otherwise used in ways that could result in the
                           identification of individual Sessional Lecturers. </item>
                        <item n="6.03.3" xml:id="s-d1e275">Personal information provided by the
                           Board under this Article shall be maintained and used by the Association
                           only for the purposes of operating the Association in accordance with the
                           provisions of the Post-Secondary Learning Act, the Freedom of Information
                           and Protection of Privacy Act, this Handbook and the Association by-laws.
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6.04" xml:id="s-d1e277">
                     <hi rend="bold">Security of Information</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="6.04.1" xml:id="s-d1e280">The Association will protect personal
                           information from unauthorized access or use. </item>
                        <item n="6.04.2" xml:id="s-d1e282">The Association will maintain in a secure
                           manner personal information obtained in accordance with this Article. </item>
                        <item n="6.04.3" xml:id="s-d1e284">The Association will inform the Board
                           immediately if it becomes known that there has been unauthorized access
                           or disclosure of personal information and will take all reasonable care
                           to prevent a recurrence. </item>
                        <item n="6.04.4" xml:id="s-d1e286">Prior to disposal of any media containing
                           personal information, the Association will ensure that such information
                           contained thereon has been erased or destroyed, and a record of disposal
                           shall be kept by the Association. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6.05" xml:id="s-d1e289">The President shall make available to the
                     Association upon written request and within a reasonable time, information on
                     Members not provided in Article <ref target="#s-d1e228">5.03</ref> and Article
                        <ref target="#s-d1e261">6.03</ref>. This section shall not be construed to
                     require the President to compile information in the form requested if such data
                     are not already compiled in the form requested, or to supply any confidential
                     information.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="7" xml:id="s-d1e265">
               <hi rend="bold">Delegation</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="7.01" xml:id="s-d1e297">Any task required herein to be performed by the
                     Board may by the Board's delegation be performed by the President. </item>
                  <item n="7.02" xml:id="s-d1e299">Any task required herein to be performed by the
                     President may be delegated by the President as he/she sees fit, and the
                     President may prescribe conditions governing the exercise of any delegated task
                     including the power of subdelegation. Any task required herein to be performed
                     by the Vice-President (Academic), or a Dean may be delegated under the same
                     provisions that apply to the President. </item>
                  <item n="7.03" xml:id="s-d1e301">Any task required herein to be performed by the
                     President of the Association may be delegated by him/her as he/she sees fit,
                     and he/she may prescribe conditions governing the exercise of any delegated
                     task including the power of subdelegation. </item>
                  <item n="7.04" xml:id="s-d1e303">Where a task required herein is delegated under
                     the provisions of this Article, the force of the performance of that task shall
                     be the same as if performed by the delegator, upon whom the results of the
                     performance shall be binding. </item>
                  <item n="7.05" xml:id="s-d1e305">The delegation of a task required herein shall be
                     made known in writing to the Members affected.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="8" xml:id="s-d1e279">
               <hi rend="bold">Personal Files</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="8.01" xml:id="s-d1e315">The appropriate Dean shall maintain a personal
                     file on each Member for purposes defined by this Handbook. This file contains
                     personal information relating to employment and educational history.</item>
                  <item n="8.02" xml:id="s-d1e317">The Member’s personal file shall not include
                     records or testimony pursuant to: <list type="unordered">
                        <item xml:id="s-d1e288">any confidential mediation process</item>
                        <item xml:id="s-d1e291">the Employee Assistance Program</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.03" xml:id="s-d1e324">Only materials relating to employment and
                     educational history and which are relevant to Handbook purposes shall be
                     entered into the file. </item>
                  <item n="8.04" xml:id="s-d1e327">All materials forming the basis of a disciplinary
                     decision regarding a Member shall have been entered in that Member’s personal
                     file. </item>
                  <item n="8.05" xml:id="s-d1e330">
                     <hi>Confidential Letters of Reference</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="8.05.1" xml:id="s-d1e334">A Member’s personal file shall include
                           all confidential letters of reference pertaining to that Member. </item>
                        <item n="8.05.2" xml:id="s-d1e336">Unless otherwise designated by the
                           author, all letters containing assessments of a Member’s performance
                           shall be deemed confidential. All confidential letters of reference shall
                           be signed and dated by their authors; letters which are not signed and
                           dated shall not enter a Member’s personal file. </item>
                        <item n="8.05.3" xml:id="s-d1e338">When a Dean of a Faculty/Dean of a School
                           requests a confidential letter of reference, he/she shall inform the
                           person requested of the provisions of this Article respecting disclosure
                           of confidential information. Before confidential information is disclosed
                           concerning letters of reference which have not been solicited by the
                           President or Faculty/Dean of a School, he/she shall inform the author of
                           the provisions of this Article. If the author requests in writing, or if
                           the author does not respond, the unsolicited letter shall be destroyed or
                           returned, whichever is more appropriate. Letters of assessment submitted
                           by a Member for inclusion on his/her personal file shall be dealt with
                           according to the provisions of Article <ref target="#s-d1e345">8.06</ref>.</item>
                        <item n="8.05.4" xml:id="s-d1e341"> A Member shall, upon written request, be
                           given by the Dean of a Faculty/Dean of a School the names of authors of
                           the confidential letters of reference in his/her personal file, and/or a
                           fair summary of the contents of those letters, except where fewer than
                           three letters are involved, in which case only the fair summary shall be
                           provided. In this context a fair summary may include quotations from or
                           non-holographic reproduction of the letter itself. The Dean of a
                           Faculty/Dean of a School shall attempt to preserve confidentiality;
                           however, the requirement of a fair summary shall take precedence over the
                           need for confidentiality where there is a clear conflict between the two
                           principles. The decision of the Dean of a Faculty/Dean of a School
                           respecting a fair summary and the manner of preservation of
                           confidentiality shall be subject to interpretation in each instance if
                           requested by the Member. The procedure for interpretation shall be as
                           provided in Article <ref target="#s-d1e54">1</ref>, except that the
                           purpose of interpretation shall be to determine whether the nature and
                           extent of confidential information disclosed satisfies the criterion of a
                           fair summary.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.06" xml:id="s-d1e345">
                     <hi>Materials Other Than Confidential Letters of Reference</hi>
                     <p>Materials other than confidential letters of reference may be placed on a
                        Member's personal file only if they are signed and dated by the author
                        and/or institutional source. The Member shall be informed within ten (10)
                        working days that materials have been placed in his/her personal file.
                        Electronic mail is considered material that is not signed.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.07" xml:id="s-d1e354">
                     <hi>Materials Obtained Pursuant to the Evaluation of Teaching</hi>.
                        <p>Materials obtained pursuant to a policy on teaching evaluation
                        established shall be dealt with according to Article <ref target="#s-d1e324">8.03</ref>. Procedures shall be used that ensure the identity of student
                        respondents is protected to the maximum extent permitted by law.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.08" xml:id="s-d1e359">Copies of documents in a Member’s personal file
                     may be made only for Sessional Lecturers Handbook purposes and such copies must
                     be destroyed when the purpose is met. </item>
                  <item n="8.09" xml:id="s-d1e361">
                     <hi>Inspection and Comment by a Member</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="8.09.1" xml:id="s-d1e364">A Member shall have the right, with
                           reasonable notice in writing, to inspect the contents of his/her personal
                           file, except for confidential letters of reference. The Member shall not
                           remove his/her personal file or any part of it. Upon written request, the
                           Member shall be able to obtain copies of the materials which he/she has
                           the right to inspect. </item>
                        <item n="8.09.2" xml:id="s-d1e366">A Member shall have the right to have
                           included in his/her personal file his/her written comments upon the
                           accuracy and/or meaning of any of the contents of that file, and to add
                           materials to the file. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.10" xml:id="s-d1e368">
                     <hi>Removal of Materials From a File</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="8.10.1" xml:id="s-d1e371">Either the Member or the President or the
                           Dean shall have the right to request in writing the removal of materials
                           included in the Member's personal file on the ground that the materials
                           do not constitute fair and/or relevant comment on the Member's
                           performance. </item>
                        <item n="8.10.2" xml:id="s-d1e373">If the President or Dean and the Member
                           agree, then the material shall be removed and destroyed or returned,
                           whichever is more appropriate. If the President or Dean do not agree, the
                           question of fair and/or relevant comment shall be submitted to
                           interpretation in each instance. The procedure for interpretation shall
                           be as provided in Article <ref target="#s-d1e54">1</ref>, except that the
                           purpose of interpretation shall be to determine whether the nature and
                           content of the material satisfies the criterion(ia) of fair and/or
                           relevant comment. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="8.11" xml:id="s-d1e375">Information contained in a personal file shall be
                     made available to persons who require access to perform their duties as
                     specified by an Article of this Handbook. In the conduct of their duties,
                     Senior Academic Administrators shall have access to the files at all times. A
                     Senior Academic Administrator may seek internal or external advice about items
                     in a Member’s personal file provided that the identity of the Member is not
                     revealed. Otherwise, the information shall be made available only as authorized
                     in writing by the Member, or as required by law. </item>
                  <item n="8.12" xml:id="s-d1e377">A Sessional Lecturer shall maintain a curriculum
                     vitae in his/her personal file. The curriculum vitae will be updated by the
                     Sessional Lecturer at the commencement of each contract period. </item>
                  <item n="8.13" xml:id="s-d1e379">A Sessional Lecturer’s personal file shall be
                     kept in accordance with the University’s Records Management Policy. </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="9" xml:id="s-d1e346">
               <hi rend="bold">Appointments</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="9.01" xml:id="s-d1e388">Whenever reasonably practicable the Board shall
                     use continuing appointments to meet the continuing staffing needs of the
                     University. However when continuing appointments are not practicable, Deans of
                     Faculties/ Deans of Schools may recommend the appointment of Sessional
                     Lecturers. </item>
                  <item n="9.02" xml:id="s-d1e390">The circumstances under which a Sessional
                     Lecturer appointment is appropriate are normally limited to the following: <list>
                        <item n="9.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e393">to replace a Member who is on leave or on
                           another assignment of duties; </item>
                        <item n="9.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e395">when the search for an individual with
                           the required qualifications for an advertised continuing position is
                           unsuccessful; </item>
                        <item n="9.02.3" xml:id="s-d1e397">when the appointment is for a pilot
                           project of limited duration; </item>
                        <item n="9.02.4" xml:id="s-d1e399">when unanticipated enrolment increases
                           makes such an appointment necessary in the short term; </item>
                        <item n="9.02.5" xml:id="s-d1e401">to integrate members of a professional
                           community into the University’s teaching program; </item>
                        <item n="9.02.6" xml:id="s-d1e403">or when a person with the required
                           qualifications fills a limited on-going pedagogical need of a Department,
                           Faculty/School curriculum. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="9.03" xml:id="s-d1e405">
                     <hi>Sessional Lecturer Appointments</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="9.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e408">The appointment of a Sessional Lecturer
                           will take into account relevant experience, academic qualifications and,
                           where appropriate, prior teaching effectiveness as determined through
                           previous performance evaluation(s) (Article <ref target="#s-d1e542">11</ref>).</item>
                        <item n="9.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e410">Sessional Lecturers appointed by a Dean
                           of Faculty/ Dean of School may teach no more than one (1) semester course
                           in a designated semester. </item>
                        <item n="9.03.3" xml:id="s-d1e412">When an appointment is made under Article
                              <ref target="#s-d1e403">9.02.6</ref>, a Sessional Lecturer contract
                           may be offered covering a number of consecutive Fall and Spring
                           semesters, in recognition of the on-going contribution of such a
                           Sessional Lecturer to the University and in light of the on-going
                           pedagogical need of a Department, Faculty or School curriculum. </item>
                        <item n="9.03.4" xml:id="s-d1e414">The appointment of Sessional Lecturers
                           must be approved by the Vice President (Academic) on behalf of the
                           Board.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="9.04" xml:id="s-d1e416">
                     <hi>Appointment Letter</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="9.04.1" xml:id="s-d1e419">The duties of a Sessional Lecturer will
                           be clearly identified by the Dean of a Faculty/ Dean of a School in a
                           letter of appointment. The letter will make reference to this agreement
                           and will identify the starting and termination dates of the contract, the
                           salary, and other relevant information. </item>
                        <item n="9.04.2" xml:id="s-d1e421">A copy of the appointment letter, in
                           which all confidential information has been removed, will be provided by
                           the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School to the Association.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="9.05" xml:id="s-d1e376">
                     <hi>Re-appointment</hi>
                     <p>At the conclusion of a Sessional Lecturer appointment, the Sessional
                        Lecturer may request in writing of the Dean who recommended the appointment
                        that the Sessional Lecturer be considered for future Sessional Lecturer
                        appointment to the same or similar semester courses, should there be a need
                        for such an appointment in the Faculty or School. Such letters shall be
                        maintained on record in the Dean’s office for a period of three (3) years
                        from the expiry of the Sessional Lecturer appointment.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="10" xml:id="s-d1e392">
               <hi rend="bold">Rights and Responsibilities</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="10.01" xml:id="s-d1e433">
                     <hi>General Rights and Responsibilities</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="10.01.1" xml:id="s-d1e436">The Board recognizes a duty to provide
                           and Members have the right to a safe workplace free from unfair
                           discrimination, harassment, or abuse of authority. </item>
                        <item n="10.01.2" xml:id="s-d1e438">
                           <hi>Complaints</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item n="10.01.2.A" xml:id="s-d1e441">Complaints about a Member
                                 pursuant to this article shall be addressed to the Member, unless
                                 the complainant has good reason to fear personal harm or offense.
                                 If so, or if the complainant is dissatisfied with the response, the
                                 complaint shall be addressed to the Member's Dean of the
                                 Faculty/Dean of the School. </item>
                              <item n="10.01.2.B" xml:id="s-d1e443">If the Dean of the Faculty/Dean
                                 of the School cannot hear, receive or act on the complaint(s) in a
                                 reasonable time, or should not hear or receive the complaint(s) for
                                 reasons of a reasonable apprehension of bias, the complaint(s)
                                 shall be referred to that person among the remaining Deans/Dean
                                 with the most decanal service at the University, and this person
                                 shall be deemed to be the appropriate Dean in accordance with
                                 Article <ref target="#s-d1e346">9</ref>. If necessary, the Office
                                 of the Vice-President (Academic) shall direct the complaint to the
                                 appropriate Dean. The Member shall be informed of the complaint
                                 immediately upon its inclusion in the Member's Personal File.
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.01.3" xml:id="s-d1e445">The Board and the Association recognize
                           Members’ rights and duties associated with academic freedom, in
                           particular, freedom to form ideas, discuss ideas, publish ideas, and
                           teach ideas which challenge opinions regarding academic and
                           administrative matters. </item>
                        <item n="10.01.4" xml:id="s-d1e447">Members shall respect the academic
                           freedom of other Members despite differences of opinion, provided
                           standards, methods and traditions of the discipline are given due
                           respect. Criticism of the ideas or performances of Members by other
                           Members or by administrators shall give due respect to these rights in
                           accordance with this Handbook. Members have a duty to exercise their own
                           academic freedom with reasonable judgment and rigour. Both parties shall
                           make efforts to promote and preserve good will among all members of the
                           University community. </item>
                        <item n="10.01.5" xml:id="s-d1e449">Clauses of this Article may be limited
                           by other Articles of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="10.02" xml:id="s-d1e451">
                     <hi>Rights of Members</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="10.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e454">
                           <hi>Discrimination</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item n="10.02.1.A" xml:id="s-d1e459">There shall be no unfair
                                 discrimination, interference, restriction or coercion practiced
                                 with respect to any Member in regard to any terms or conditions of
                                 employment by reason of age, race, colour, ethnicity, national
                                 origin, philosophical, political, or religious affiliation or
                                 belief, gender, sexual orientation, marital status, or physical
                                 disability. </item>
                              <item n="10.02.1.B" xml:id="s-d1e461">There shall be no unfair
                                 discrimination practiced with respect to any Member in regard to
                                 any terms or conditions of employment by reason of family
                                 relationships. However, no Member shall take part in formal
                                 discussions or vote with regard to the determination of the terms
                                 and conditions of employment of a member of his/her immediate
                                 family. </item>
                              <item n="10.02.1.C" xml:id="s-d1e463">The Board may conduct research
                                 to determine if unfair discrimination has occurred. </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e465">
                           <hi>Participation and Accompaniment</hi>
                           <p>Except as provided in Article <ref target="#s-d1e451">10.02</ref>,
                              Members shall have the right to express opinions and to participate by
                              means of their representatives in procedures provided by this
                              Handbook. Members have the right to be accompanied by another Member
                              of the Association in all procedures specified in this Handbook. A
                              Member exerting this right is under no obligation to justify the need
                              to be accompanied by a Member of his/her choice. A Member may waive
                              his/her right to accompaniment.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.02.3" xml:id="s-d1e470">
                           <hi>Representation to the Board</hi>
                           <p>A Member shall have the right to make written representation to the
                              Board through the President.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.02.4" xml:id="s-d1e475">
                           <hi>Other Rights</hi>
                           <p>Members have the right, consistent with policies of General Faculties
                              Council to:</p>
                           <list>
                              <item n="10.02.4.A" xml:id="s-d1e480">maintain order and safety in the
                                 classroom, lab or other teaching or research situation and to limit
                                 the access of persons who are abusive, disruptive or who otherwise
                                 violate the rights of Members, students, or other people authorized
                                 to be present. </item>
                              <item n="10.02.4.B" xml:id="s-d1e482">assistance of security personnel
                                 regarding the maintenance of such order, safety and limitations of
                                 access. </item>
                              <item n="10.02.4.C" xml:id="s-d1e484">the right to rule on the use by
                                 students of recording devices in the classroom, laboratory, or
                                 analogous learning situation, subject to reasonable accommodation
                                 of student needs. </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.02.5" xml:id="s-d1e486">Sessional Lecturers are entitled to
                           office space, access to University technology appropriate to their
                           duties, and to library facilities and privileges. </item>
                        <item n="10.02.6" xml:id="s-d1e488">
                           <hi>Relationship to the Community</hi>
                           <p>When addressing themselves to the community at large, Members retain
                              the rights and responsibilities which flow from the concept of
                              academic freedom.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.02.7" xml:id="s-d1e493">The capacity and duty of the Association
                           to act on behalf of the Member shall be in effect as long as procedures
                           may be initiated under the terms of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook with
                           respect to that Member, and/or as long as a personal file is maintained
                           on that Member under Article <ref target="#s-d1e279">8</ref>. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="10.03" xml:id="s-d1e495">
                     <hi>Responsibilities of Members</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="10.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e497">
                           <hi>Responsibilities of Members as Teachers</hi>
                           <p>Members shall have the following responsibilities as teachers:</p>
                           <list>
                              <item n="10.03.1.A" xml:id="s-d1e503">Members shall maintain a
                                 scholarly competence and pedagogic effectiveness. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.B" xml:id="s-d1e505">Members shall discharge their
                                 instructional responsibilities in accordance with procedures
                                 established pursuant to the provisions of the Post-Secondary
                                 Learning Act. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.C" xml:id="s-d1e507">Members who provide instruction
                                 shall comply with procedures established pursuant to the provisions
                                 of the Post-Secondary Learning Act for reporting the grades of
                                 their students. Where such grades are reviewed by Department,
                                 School, Faculty or University committees, Members should be
                                 available for the duration of the committee's work if so required
                                 by the committee. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.D" xml:id="s-d1e509">Members shall not cancel or
                                 terminate scheduled instruction except for good reason and shall
                                 give their students notice of such cancellation together with
                                 notice of any alternative instruction or rescheduling of the
                                 cancelled instruction. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.E" xml:id="s-d1e511">Members must report any absences
                                 from class to the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School or to
                                 their immediate supervisor. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.F" xml:id="s-d1e513">Members shall be reasonably
                                 available for out of class consultation with students. Students
                                 shall have equal opportunity for such consultation. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.G" xml:id="s-d1e515">Members shall treat students
                                 fairly in class and shall reasonably accommodate individual
                                 instructional needs. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.H" xml:id="s-d1e517">Members shall not accept pay for
                                 tutoring a student in any subjects in which the Member is
                                 responsible for giving classroom instruction to that student, but
                                 may recommend tutors who may do so provided that no benefit, direct
                                 or indirect, accrues to the Member for that referral. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.I" xml:id="s-d1e519">A Member shall not require
                                 students to provide any services to the Member outside a formal,
                                 employer/employee relationship. Any employer/employee relationship
                                 entered into by a Member shall be reported by the Member to his/her
                                 Dean. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.J" xml:id="s-d1e521">Sessional Lecturers may not
                                 supervise graduate students, evaluate graduate students or be a
                                 member of a graduate student supervisory committee. </item>
                              <item n="10.03.1.K" xml:id="s-d1e523">A personal, intimate
                                 relationship is one where there exists reasonable apprehension of
                                 bias between a Sessional Lecturer and a student, and which may be
                                 perceived as conferring upon one of them an unfair advantage or
                                 subject one of them to unfair disadvantage. Such relationships may
                                 therefore be perceived as a conflict of interest with respect to
                                 any evaluative relationship between the Sessional Lecturer and the
                                    student.<p>A Sessional Lecturer who is involved in a personal,
                                    intimate relationship with a student with whom the Sessional
                                    Lecturer will likely have an evaluative relationship must
                                    disclose this personal, intimate relationship in writing to the
                                    Dean/University Librarian prior to the commencement of any
                                    evaluative relationship between the Sessional Lecturer and the
                                    student. A Sessional Lecturer who becomes involved in a
                                    personal, intimate relationship with a student with whom the
                                    Sessional Lecturer has an evaluative relationship has an
                                    obligation to disclose this personal, intimate relationship in
                                    writing to the Sessional Lecturer’s Dean/University
                                    Librarian.</p>
                                 <p>The Dean/University Librarian shall take the necessary action to
                                    ensure that any such evaluation is performed in a fair and
                                    reasonable manner.</p>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e530">
                           <hi>Participation of Members as Scholars</hi>
                           <p>Sessional Lecturers are not required to conduct research; however,
                              research activity which does not interfere with or prevent the
                              fulfillment of the assigned teaching responsibilities, as identified
                              within the Sessional Lecturers contract, shall not be discouraged.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item n="10.03.3" xml:id="s-d1e535">
                           <hi>Participation of Members in Administrative and Committee Work</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item n="10.03.3.A" xml:id="s-d1e538">Sessional Lecturers may be
                                 invited to participate in Department, Faculty/School meetings
                                 however the degree of participation may vary from Member to
                                 Member.</item>
                              <item n="10.03.3.B" xml:id="s-d1e540">Sessional Lecturers have the
                                 right and are encouraged to become involved with the work of the
                                 Association. However, this work should not interfere with or
                                 prevent the fulfillment of the assigned teaching responsibilities
                                 as identified within the Sessional Lecturer’s contract. </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="11" xml:id="s-d1e542">
               <hi rend="bold">Performance Evaluation</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="11.01" xml:id="s-d1e546">It is a Member’s responsibility to present
                     evidence of teaching effectiveness. </item>
                  <item n="11.02" xml:id="s-d1e548">No assessment of teaching effectiveness shall be
                     based mainly on student appraisals. The methods of teaching evaluation may vary
                     but may include student appraisals, Chair assessment, assessments by Faculty
                     Members/Instructors/Academic Assistants, evaluation of course material and
                     examinations, and other relevant considerations. </item>
                  <item n="11.03" xml:id="s-d1e550">Evidence of teaching effectiveness shall be
                     submitted to the Dean of the Faculty/ Dean of the School. </item>
                  <item n="11.04" xml:id="s-d1e552">Where a written assessment of a Sessional
                     Lecturer’s teaching effectiveness has been made, then the Sessional Lecturer
                     will be provided with a copy of that written assessment. The Sessional Lecturer
                     will also be provided with the compiled summary of any student appraisals in
                     courses taught by the Sessional Lecturer.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="12" xml:id="s-d1e528">
               <hi rend="bold">Termination of Appointment</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="12.01" xml:id="s-d1e560">The term of appointment shall be included within
                     the letter of appointment. There is no obligation on the University to extend
                     the appointment beyond the term or to reappoint the Sessional Lecturer. </item>
                  <item n="12.02" xml:id="s-d1e562">A Sessional Lecturer may resign during the term
                     of appointment. The Sessional Lecturer will give one month notice in writing to
                     the Dean of the School who made the original appointment. </item>
                  <item n="12.03" xml:id="s-d1e564">Termination of a Sessional Lecturer’s
                     appointment by dismissal is described within Article <ref target="#s-d1e600">15</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="12.04" xml:id="s-d1e566">Mutual Agreement Either the Dean or a Sessional
                     Lecturer may at any time propose termination of the Sessional Lecturer's
                     appointment under mutually acceptable terms.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="13" xml:id="s-d1e539">
               <hi rend="bold">Compensation and Benefits</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="13.01" xml:id="s-d1e574">Stipend A minimum stipend, exclusive of holiday
                     pay and other statutory benefits, shall be established through negotiations
                     between the Board and the Association, and shall be provided in this Handbook
                     as “Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e803">A</ref>: Stipend”. The stipend shall be
                     paid in monthly instalments.</item>
                  <item n="13.02" xml:id="s-d1e576">Economic benefits shall be as set forth in
                     Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e837">B</ref>.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="14" xml:id="s-d1e547">
               <hi rend="bold">Grievance Procedure</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="14.01" xml:id="s-d1e587">A grievance is a claim that there has been a
                     violation, improper application or non-application of the terms of this
                     Handbook. A grievance shall be settled in accordance with the terms of this
                        Handbook.<p>The following matters shall not be subject to grievance:</p>
                     <list>
                        <item n="14.01.1" xml:id="s-d1e592">The outcome of a specific process
                           provided by this Handbook that is binding on both parties,</item>
                        <item n="14.01.2" xml:id="s-d1e594">A request for amendment of this
                           Handbook,</item>
                        <item n="14.01.3" xml:id="s-d1e596">A matter not covered by this Handbook.
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="14.02" xml:id="s-d1e598">A grievance shall be claimed in writing
                     specifying the term(s) to which the grievance applies within twenty (20)
                     working days of the date on which the violation or improper application is
                     alleged to have occurred, or within twenty (20) working days from the date in
                     which the alleged violation should have become known to the Member or
                     President. A grievance may be claimed by a Member, by the Association or by the
                     President.</item>
                  <item n="14.03" xml:id="s-d1e602">Before claiming a grievance, the grievor shall
                     meet with the President, or the President of the Association, as appropriate,
                     in an attempt to resolve the issue. The parties to this meeting may have a
                     representative or advisor of his or her choice also attend the meeting. If the
                     issue is not resolved by this meeting, the grievor may proceed to claim the
                     grievance in the manner described within this Article. The timing of this
                     meeting shall not affect the application of Article <ref target="#s-d1e598">14.02</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="14.04" xml:id="s-d1e604">In the event that the President claims a
                     grievance against the Association, the President shall present the grievance in
                     writing, specifying the terms to which the grievance applies and providing such
                     evidence as appropriate to support the grievance, to the President of the
                     Association. If the matter is not resolved to the satisfaction of the President
                     within fifteen (15) working days of the Association having received the
                     grievance, the President may refer the matter to arbitration as specified in
                     Article <ref target="#s-d1e622">14.08</ref>. If the matter is to be referred to
                     arbitration, the President will provide notice to the President of the
                     Association of the referral.</item>
                  <item n="14.05" xml:id="s-d1e606">A Member intending to claim a grievance shall
                     first present the claim to the Association, which shall decide within fifteen
                     (15) working days whether to claim the grievance. The Member may claim the
                     grievance on his/her own behalf only if the Association does not undertake a
                     claim of grievance arising from the claim of the Member. In such a case, the
                     Association shall not take further action under the provisions of this Article
                     respecting the grievance of the Member. </item>
                  <item n="14.06" xml:id="s-d1e608">In the event that the Member/Association claims
                     a grievance the process shall be as follows: <list>
                        <item n="14.06.1" xml:id="s-d1e610">The grievance shall be presented in
                           writing, specifying the term(s) to which the grievance applies and
                           providing such evidence as appropriate to support the grievance to the
                           President.</item>
                        <item n="14.06.2" xml:id="s-d1e612">The President shall investigate the
                           grievance as he/she deems appropriate, and shall present a written report
                           to the Association/Member within ten (10) working days together with a
                           recommendation to resolve the dispute. </item>
                        <item n="14.06.3" xml:id="s-d1e614">The President's report shall be deemed
                           accepted by the Member/Association and a satisfactory resolution of the
                           grievance affected, unless within five (5) working days of receipt by the
                           Member, the Member/Association notifies the President in writing to the
                           contrary. If such notification is given, the President and the
                           Member/Association shall meet within five (5) working days to attempt to
                           resolve the grievance. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="14.07" xml:id="s-d1e617">In the event that the President and the
                     Member/Association are unable to resolve the grievance at their meeting, then
                     the Member/Association shall within thirty (30) working days of their meeting
                     notify the President that he/she refers the matter to arbitration. If the
                     Member/Association does not so notify the President within thirty (30) working
                     days, the grievance will be deemed to have been abandoned and no further action
                     shall take place under the provisions of this Article. </item>
                  <item n="14.08" xml:id="s-d1e622"> When arbitration is required, grievances shall
                     be referred to a single arbitrator. The arbitrator shall be appointed by the
                     agreement of the President of the University and the Member/President of the
                     Association within five (5) working days after the President or the President
                     of the Association, as appropriate, has received notice of referral. Failing
                     agreement within those seven days, the arbitrator shall be appointed by a Judge
                     of the Alberta Court of Queen's Bench upon the Petition of either party. </item>
                  <item n="14.09" xml:id="s-d1e626">For the purposes of Article <ref target="#s-d1e547">14</ref>, and subject to the particular provisions below,
                     the arbitrator shall conduct the arbitration and assign the costs of
                     arbitration in accordance with the provisions of the Arbitration Act of the
                     Province of Alberta: <list>
                        <item n="14.09.1" xml:id="s-d1e629">The arbitrator shall have no power to
                           add to, delete, or otherwise amend this Sessional Lecturers Handbook. </item>
                        <item n="14.09.2" xml:id="s-d1e631">The arbitrator shall confine him/herself
                           to the grievance submitted for arbitration and shall have no authority to
                           determine any other issues not so submitted to him/her. </item>
                        <item n="14.09.3" xml:id="s-d1e633">When dealing with a grievance involving
                           claim of noncompliance with procedural requirements, if the arbitrator
                           finds that the procedural requirements have not been complied with,
                           he/she shall be limited to directing that the matter be reconsidered by
                           the appropriate body in accordance with the procedures specified in the
                           appropriate article. </item>
                        <item n="14.09.4" xml:id="s-d1e635">The arbitrator shall hear the grievance
                           and issue a decision that shall be final and binding upon the parties to
                           the arbitration. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="14.10" xml:id="s-d1e637">All dates and times in this Article may be
                     varied by mutual consent of the parties. </item>
                  <item n="14.11" xml:id="s-d1e639">Interpretations, clarifications or
                     specifications of this Handbook, either agreed upon by both parties or ruled by
                     an arbitrator as part of the resolution of grievances, may be incorporated as
                     clauses or schedules of this Handbook. </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="15" xml:id="s-d1e600">
               <hi rend="bold">Discipline</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="15.01" xml:id="s-d1e648">A Sessional Lecturer may be disciplined for
                     just, reasonable, and sufficient cause, in accordance with the provisions of
                     this Article. </item>
                  <item n="15.02" xml:id="s-d1e650">The only disciplinary measures which may be
                     taken by the Board against a Sessional Lecturer are the following:<list>
                        <item n="15.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e655">a letter of reprimand or censure may be
                           placed in the Personal File of the Sessional Lecturer; </item>
                        <item n="15.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e657">the Sessional Lecturer may be dismissed
                           for cause, in which case cause shall mean professional incompetence
                           and/or gross misconduct and/or serious and persistent neglect of duty.
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="15.03" xml:id="s-d1e659">
                     <hi rend="bold">Disciplinary Process</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="15.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e664">When a Dean of a Faculty/Dean of a
                           School has reasonable cause to believe that cause may exist for the
                           discipline of a Sessional Lecturer, the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the
                           School will meet with the Sessional Lecturer to seek a response to the
                           allegations against the Sessional Lecturer. </item>
                        <item n="15.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e668">Following the meeting in Article <ref target="#s-d1e664">15.03.1</ref>, the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the
                           School may: impose one of the disciplinary measures identified in Article
                              <ref target="#s-d1e650">15.02</ref>; decline to proceed further with
                           the disciplinary process. </item>
                        <item n="15.03.3" xml:id="s-d1e672">When the process under Article <ref target="#s-d1e659">15.03</ref> has been commenced by the Dean of the
                           Faculty/Dean of the School, the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School
                           will inform the Sessional Lecturer in writing, with respect to the Dean’s
                           decision under Article <ref target="#s-d1e668">15.03.2</ref>.</item>
                        <item n="15.03.4" xml:id="s-d1e676">Within five (5) working days of the
                           Dean’s letter of Article <ref target="#s-d1e672">15.03.3</ref>, the
                           Sessional Lecturer may appeal the decision of the Dean of the
                           Faculty/Dean of the School to a University Internal Arbitration
                           Committee. </item>
                        <item n="15.03.5" xml:id="s-d1e678">The University Internal Arbitration
                           Committee is comprised of three persons: one selected by the Sessional
                           Lecturer; one selected by the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School; one
                           person previously named by the President of the Association and the
                           President of the University. </item>
                        <item n="15.03.6" xml:id="s-d1e680">The President of the Association and the
                           President of the University will agree upon the name of the third person
                           of the University Internal Arbitration Committee at their annual meeting
                           (Article <ref target="#s-d1e714">19</ref>).</item>
                        <item n="15.03.7" xml:id="s-d1e684">The University Internal Arbitration
                           Committee will review the appeal and come to a decision on the matter.
                           The decision of the University Internal Arbitration Committee shall be
                           final and not subject to further appeal. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="15.04" xml:id="s-d1e686">The financial cost associated with the
                     arbitration process will be divided equally between the Association and the
                     Board. </item>
                  <item n="15.05" xml:id="s-d1e688">All materials pertaining to the Sessional
                     Lecturer which are used pursuant to the Article shall be deemed part of the
                     Sessional Lecturer’s Personal File, subject to the provisions of Article <ref target="#s-d1e279">8</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="15.06" xml:id="s-d1e690">Wherever possible, actions pursuant to this
                     Article shall be expeditious. Specified time limits may be extended by mutual
                     consent, given in writing and signed by both parties.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="16" xml:id="s-d1e636">
               <hi rend="bold">Holidays</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="16.01" xml:id="s-d1e698">The following days are statutory holidays: New
                     Year's Day, Family Day, Good Friday, Easter Monday, Victoria Day, Canada Day,
                     Civic Holiday, Labour Day, Thanksgiving Day, Remembrance Day, Christmas Day,
                     Boxing Day and any other day so proclaimed by the Federal, Provincial,
                     Municipal or University authorities. </item>
                  <item n="16.02" xml:id="s-d1e700">When any of the aforementioned holidays fall on
                     a Saturday or Sunday, the President shall designate the working day immediately
                     preceding or following as the holiday. </item>
                  <item n="16.03" xml:id="s-d1e704">Notwithstanding Article <ref target="#s-d1e700">16.02</ref>, Sessional Lecturers will ensure adherence to the instructional
                     time per academic course and the identified number of classes per course as
                     described in the Academic Schedule of the most recently published edition of
                     the University Calendar. </item>
                  <item n="16.04" xml:id="s-d1e706">A Member shall not receive additional
                     remuneration in the event he/she chooses to work on a holiday. </item>
                  <item n="16.05" xml:id="s-d1e708">Regularly scheduled classes shall not be held on
                     a holiday.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="17" xml:id="s-d1e651">
               <hi rend="bold">Medical Leave</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="17.01" xml:id="s-d1e716">A Sessional Lecturer may be absent for medical
                     reasons for up to five (5) working days without reduction in salary or
                     benefits. </item>
                  <item n="17.02" xml:id="s-d1e718">The Sessional Lecturer shall inform the
                     Department Chair or immediate supervisor of his/her absence as soon as
                     possible, and provide an estimate of its duration. The Sessional Lecturer may
                     provide a medical certificate to the Department Chair or immediate supervisor. </item>
                  <item n="17.03" xml:id="s-d1e720">When a Sessional Lecturer has been absent for
                     medical reasons for five (5) working days or if the Sessional Lecturer
                     contemplates the medical leave will be for longer than five (5) working days
                     he/she will provide a medical certificate to his/her Department Chair or
                     immediate supervisor. </item>
                  <item n="17.04" xml:id="s-d1e722">When the Sessional Lecturer has been absent for
                     medical reasons for more than five (5) working days, he/she will be placed on
                     medical leave without pay, until such time as he/she is able to return to work
                     and resume duties. </item>
                  <item n="17.05" xml:id="s-d1e724">Normally after ten (10) working days of medical
                     leave there will be no resumption of the duties specified within the Sessional
                     Lecturer’s contract. </item>
                  <item n="17.06" xml:id="s-d1e726">
                     <hi>Special Circumstances</hi>
                     <p>Upon application by the Member and recommendation of the Dean of the
                        Faculty/Dean of the School and the President, the Board may award leave
                        under family or medical circumstances which reasonably warrant it, not
                        elsewhere specified in this Article. The rate of pay, if any, and the
                        applicability of other Articles of this Handbook shall be specified by the
                        Board and accepted in writing by the Member prior to the award to leave.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="18" xml:id="s-d1e670">
               <hi rend="bold">Copyright and Patents</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="18.01" xml:id="s-d1e737">
                     <hi>Copyright</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="18.01.1" xml:id="s-d1e740">If a Member is appointed to prepare
                           specific works for the University, or if the normal assignment of a
                           Member includes the preparation of specific works, then the Board is the
                           owner of the copyright and all copyright works produced by the
                           Member.</item>
                        <item n="18.01.2" xml:id="s-d1e744">The rights and obligations of the Board
                           and of the Member with respect to copyright and other rights and works
                           produced by Members under the provisions of Article <ref target="#s-d1e740">18.01.1</ref> shall be set forth as follows:<list>
                              <item n="18.01.2.A" xml:id="s-d1e748">The Board will normally transfer
                                 its ownership rights on such material to the author (or group of
                                 authors) upon the condition that the author agrees to the
                                 conditions in Article <ref target="#s-d1e757">18.01.2.D</ref>.</item>
                              <item n="18.01.2.B" xml:id="s-d1e751">Any author who desires to secure
                                 the ownership of copyright shall apply to the President for such
                                 transfer on an Assignment of Copyright Form as provided in Schedule
                                    <ref target="#s-d1e887">D</ref>.</item>
                              <item n="18.01.2.C" xml:id="s-d1e754">Before such application is made,
                                 the applicant shall have obtained agreement from all those involved
                                 in the production process of the said material upon the
                                 identification of the authors and shall file a declaration thereto
                                 along with the application.</item>
                              <item n="18.01.2.D" xml:id="s-d1e757">The Board will transfer by
                                 written agreement its ownership rights to the designated material
                                 under the following conditions:<list>
                                    <item n="18.01.2.D.I" xml:id="s-d1e762">that the Board shall
                                       have unhampered use of the material for its internal
                                       educational purposes, including both instruction and
                                       research.</item>
                                    <item n="18.01.2.D.II" xml:id="s-d1e764">that the author(s)
                                       named in the agreement shall return to the Board fifty per
                                       cent (50%) of the royalty, or any payments which are similar
                                       in nature to royalty, the author(s) may receive from the
                                       copyright.</item>
                                    <item n="18.01.2.D.III" xml:id="s-d1e766">that the author(s), if
                                       so requested by the Board, shall display the University’s
                                       name on the particular product of which the ownership of
                                       copyright is being transferred.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item n="18.01.2.E" xml:id="s-d1e768">Upon receipt of its share of the
                                 royalties from the author(s) in any such agreement the Board shall
                                 transfer ninety per cent (90%) of that share to the Department or
                                 Departments named in the agreement. If there is more than one
                                 Department involved, the Board will divide the percentage among the
                                 Departments in a manner to be agreed by the Departments in the
                                 transfer agreement. The remaining ten per cent (10%) of the money
                                 received by the Board shall be transferred to the Media
                                 Distribution Centre. At the time of transfer, Departments may elect
                                 to have funds credited to either operating or capital accounts but
                                 they must be expended during the fiscal year in which the transfer
                                 is made. The Board will vary the 90% / 10% split in favour of the
                                 Media Distribution Centre upon direction of the Department(s) named
                                 in the agreement.</item>
                              <item n="18.01.2.F" xml:id="s-d1e771">Materials covered by this
                                 article include video and audio recordings, films, film loops,
                                 slides, transparencies, phonograph recordings, and kinescope
                                 productions, but do not include unrecorded lectures, performances,
                                 broadcasts and works of art.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="18.01.3" xml:id="s-d1e775">Except for the cases referred to in
                           Article <ref target="#s-d1e740">18.01.1</ref> and Article <ref target="#s-d1e748">18.01.2.A</ref>, <ref target="#s-d1e751">18.01.2.B</ref>, <ref target="#s-d1e754">18.01.2.C</ref>, <ref target="#s-d1e757">18.01.2.D</ref>, <ref target="#s-d1e768">18.01.2.E</ref>, and <ref target="#s-d1e771">18.01.2.F</ref>, the Board waives, disclaims and abandons
                           all right, title, interest or estate in a copyright work produced by a
                           Member.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="18.02" xml:id="s-d1e777">
                     <hi>Patents</hi>
                     <p>A Member who in the course of his/her normal performance of duties makes an
                        invitation or discovery may apply for a patent independent of the Board.
                        Subject to the agreement of the Member concerned, the Board may acquire a
                        right, title, interest or estate in such a patent.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="18.03" xml:id="s-d1e782">
                     <hi>Interpretation of ‘specific works’ and ‘normal assignment’ as used in
                        Article <ref target="#s-d1e740">18.01.1</ref>
                     </hi>
                     <p>In Article <ref target="#s-d1e740">18.01.1</ref>, ‘specific works’ shall
                        mean antecedently named and described works prepared by a Member. Those
                        categories on which ‘specific works’ may be included are listed in Article
                           <ref target="#s-d1e771">18.01.2.F</ref> ‘Normal assignment’ shall not be
                        construed in such a way as to infringe upon a Member’s academic freedom to
                        choose his/her own area of research within his/her discipline.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="19" xml:id="s-d1e714">
               <hi rend="bold">Annual Meeting</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="19.01" xml:id="s-d1e794">The President of the University and the
                     President of the Association shall, by October 15 of each year, agree to a date
                     for a meeting of representatives of the Board and the Association. </item>
                  <item n="19.02" xml:id="s-d1e796">Each party shall submit to the other not less
                     than five (5) working days before the scheduled date of the meeting a list of
                     particular matters to be discussed including the name of the third person of
                     the University Internal Arbitration Committee as provided within Article
                     <ref target="#s-d1e680">15.03.6</ref>. </item>
                  <item n="19.03" xml:id="s-d1e798">No more than five (5) representatives from each
                     party shall attend such meetings. </item>
                  <item n="19.04" xml:id="s-d1e800">Matters that would normally be dealt with in
                     Article <ref target="#s-d1e547">14</ref> shall not be the subject matter of these meetings.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list ana="schedule">
            <item n="A" xml:id="s-d1e803" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Stipend</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="A.01" xml:id="s-d1e806">
                     <hi>Minimum Sessional Lecturer Stipend:</hi>
                     <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                           <cell>Effective September 1, 2015 to April 30, 2016</cell>
                           <cell>$6,000.00 per course</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Effective May 1, 2016 to April 30, 2017</cell>
                           <cell>$6,084 per course</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Effective May 1, 2017 to April 30, 2018</cell>
                           <cell> $6,084 +COLA per course* *(Rounded to the nearest dollar) </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <p>For the purposes of this Schedule, Cost of Living Allowance (COLA) is the
                        greater of 0% or the COLA formula. The COLA formula is defined as the
                        following percentage: (Canadian CPI + Alberta CPI)/2, with CPI (Consumer
                        Price Index) being the annual CPI percentage change as published by
                        Statistics Canada, to the end of February of the year in which the COLA is
                        applied.</p>
                     <p>The rate for Sessional Lecturer course stipends will be at least the minimum
                        stipend exclusive of vacation pay and other statutory benefits, the exact
                        amount to be negotiated by the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School and
                        the Sessional Lecturer.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="A.02" xml:id="s-d1e832">
                     <hi>Course Cancellation</hi>
                     <p>Ten percent (10%) of the stipend agreed upon and declared within the letter
                        of appointment shall be paid to the Sessional Lecturer in the event the
                        course is cancelled by the Dean of the Faculty/Dean of the School who made
                        the appointment.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="B" xml:id="s-d1e837" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Benefits</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="B.01" xml:id="s-d1e840">In the event of the death of a Sessional
                     Lecturer, the Board shall pay to the Member’s estate a death benefit equivalent
                     in value to the Member’s salary for the month in which the Member dies plus one
                     additional month’s salary regardless of the month in which the Sessional
                     Lecturer dies. Such payment is in full settlement of salary and vacation
                     entitlement to the date of death.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="C" xml:id="s-d1e843" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Negotiations and Impasse</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="C.01" xml:id="s-d1e846">Individual and/or group salary matters,
                     compensation, perquisites, benefit plans, emoluments, not included in Schedules
                     A and B may be put forward by either party for negotiation. For any such matter
                     to become a negotiable matter it must be agreed to by both parties. If an
                     impasse to mutual agreement results, the impasse shall be resolved by Final
                     Offer Selection (FOS). The decision of the Arbitrator shall be binding. </item>
                  <item n="C.02" xml:id="s-d1e848">
                     <hi>Procedures and Timing</hi>
                     <p>The timing of negotiation of amendments shall follow the schedule defined in
                        Article <ref target="#s-d1e180">3.02</ref>.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item n="C.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e854">During the month of November of a year in
                           which the compensation contract as provided in Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e803">A</ref> is to expire, and prior to negotiations,
                           the Board and the Association shall jointly agree on an Arbitrator for
                           purposes of final offer selection (FOS). As per past practice, both
                           parties will continue to exchange names until such time as one name is
                           deemed mutually acceptable, or must be drawn by lot. </item>
                        <item n="C.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e856">Not later than February 1 of a year in
                           which the compensation contract as provided in Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e803">A</ref> is to expire, and prior to negotiations,
                           the Board and the Association shall appoint duly authorized negotiating
                           teams and communicate the names to the other party. Shortly thereafter,
                           the parties will meet to exchange initial positions and set a schedule
                           for negotiations. </item>
                        <item n="C.02.3" xml:id="s-d1e858">
                           <p>(a) The negotiating teams shall meet as necessary to negotiate in good
                              faith towards settlement of the items for negotiation.</p>
                           <p>(b) Each negotiating team may use the services of such consultants and
                              resource persons as it sees fit. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item n="C.02.4" xml:id="s-d1e867"> If negotiations between the parties
                           reach an impasse, then negotiations shall cease. Each negotiating team
                           shall prepare and deliver to the other a written statement of its final
                           position with respect to each unresolved item for negotiation and a brief
                           written statement of its arguments. Negotiations shall then be reopened.
                           In the event that any of the items for negotiation have not been resolved
                           within ten (10) working days of re-opening negotiations, then
                           negotiations shall again cease. </item>
                        <item n="C.02.5" xml:id="s-d1e871">
                           <hi>Arbitration</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item n="C.02.5.A" xml:id="s-d1e874">Each party shall submit to the
                                 Arbitrator the written statement (prepared for Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e858">C.02.3</ref>) of its’ final position with
                                 respect to each unresolved item for negotiation and a brief written
                                 statement of its arguments. </item>
                              <item n="C.02.5.B" xml:id="s-d1e876">The Arbitrator may hold a hearing
                                 with both negotiating teams together, i.e. not separately, for the
                                 purpose of seeking clarification of the submissions. </item>
                              <item n="C.02.5.C" xml:id="s-d1e878">The Arbitrator shall select one
                                 of the two final positions submitted to him/her pursuant to the
                                 provisions of Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e867">C.02.4</ref> and
                                 forthwith communicate his/her decision in writing to the Chair of
                                 the Board and the President of the Association. </item>
                              <item n="C.02.5.D" xml:id="s-d1e880">The Arbitrator is not required to
                                 state any reasons for the selection he/she has made. </item>
                              <item n="C.02.5.E" xml:id="s-d1e882">The decision of the Arbitrator,
                                 and the implications of his/her selection, shall be binding on both
                                 parties subject to any provincial or federal legislation that takes
                                 precedence. </item>
                              <item n="C.02.5.F" xml:id="s-d1e884">The fees and expenses of the
                                 Arbitrator shall be shared equally between the Board and the
                                 Association.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="D" xml:id="s-d1e887" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Copyright</hi>
               <list>
                  <item n="D.01" xml:id="s-d1e890">Under the provisions of the Post-Secondary
                     Learning Act and Article <ref target="#s-d1e670">18</ref> of the Sessional Lecturers Handbook, the University
                     asserts its copyright ownership on works produced by a Member who has been
                     engaged by the University for the express purpose of preparing such works for
                     the University and part of his/her normal responsibility to the University is
                     the preparation of such works. </item>
                  <item n="D.02" xml:id="s-d1e892">The University will normally transfer its
                     ownership rights on such material to the author (or group of authors) upon the
                     condition that the author agrees to the conditions in Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e898">D.05</ref>.</item>
                  <item n="D.03" xml:id="s-d1e894">Any author who desires to secure the ownership of
                     copyright shall apply to the President for such transfer on an Assignment of
                     Copyright Form. </item>
                  <item n="D.04" xml:id="s-d1e896">Before such application is made, the applicant
                     shall have obtained agreement from all those involved in the production process
                     of the said material upon the identification of the authors and shall file a
                     declaration thereto along with the application. </item>
                  <item n="D.05" xml:id="s-d1e898"> The University will transfer by written
                     agreement its ownership rights to the designated material under the following
                     conditions: <list>
                        <item n="D.05.1" xml:id="s-d1e903">that the University shall have unhampered
                           use of the material for its internal educational purposes, including both
                           instruction and research. </item>
                        <item n="D.05.2" xml:id="s-d1e905">that the author named in the agreement
                           shall return to the University fifty per cent (50%) of the royalty the
                           author may receive from the copyright. </item>
                        <item n="D.05.3" xml:id="s-d1e907">that the author, if so requested by the
                           University, shall display the University's name on the particular product
                           of which the ownership of copyright is being transferred. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="D.06" xml:id="s-d1e909">Upon receipt of its share of the royalties from
                     the author(s) in any such agreement the University shall transfer ninety per
                     cent (90%) of that share to the Department or Departments named in the
                     agreement. If there is more than one Department involved, the University will
                     divide the percentage among the Departments in a manner to be agreed by the
                     Departments in the transfer agreement. The remaining ten per cent (10%) of the
                     money received by the University shall be transferred to the Media Distribution
                     Centre. At the time of transfer, Departments may elect to have funds credited
                     to either operating or capital accounts but they must be expended during the
                     fiscal year in which the transfer is made. The University will vary the 90%/10%
                     split in favour of the Media Distribution Centre upon direction of the
                     Department(s) named in the agreement. </item>
                  <item n="D.07" xml:id="s-d1e911">Materials covered by this Schedule include
                     videotapes, audiotapes, films, film loops, slides, transparencies, phonograph
                     recordings, and kinescope productions, but do not include unrecorded lectures,
                     performances, broadcasts and works of art.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item n="E" xml:id="s-d1e813" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">ASSIGNMENT OF COPYRIGHT FORM</hi>
               <p>
                  <lb/>ASSIGNMENT made this ________ day of ________ 20____.<lb/>
                  <lb/>BETWEEN:<lb/> THE BOARD OF GOVERNORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF LETHBRIDGE <lb/>
                  (herein called “the Board”)<lb/>
                  <lb/>AND:<lb/>
                  <lb/>(herein called “the Assignees”)<lb/>
                  <lb/>WITNESS that the Board hereby sells, assigns and transfers to the assignees
                  all right, title and interest that the said Board has in copyright in Canada, the
                  United States of America and all other countries in the world in the product in
                  consideration for which the Assignees hereby agree to remit to the Board Fifty Per
                  Cent (50%) of the gross royalties (or any payments which are similar in nature to
                  royalties) received from exploitation of the copyright on the product described
                  above and also agree to require the display of the University name on all copies
                  of the product.<lb/>
                  <lb/>The Assignees further agree that the Board may make and use copies of the
                  product described above without payment of royalty for its own educational purposes.<lb/>
                  <lb/> IN WITNESS WHEREOF the parties have hereunto set their hands and seals.<lb/>
                  <lb/>THE GOVERNORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF LETHBRIDGE<lb/>
                  <lb/>ASSIGNEES<lb/>
                  <lb/> DECLARATION OF AUTHORSHIP <lb/>
                  <lb/>We, the undersigned, declare that we are the authors of: _______________(“the
                  work”) for which we have requested an assignment of copyright, dated the _______
                  day of ________________ 20____ from the Governors of the University of Lethbridge.<lb/>
                  <lb/>We further declare that we have discussed our application for assignment of
                  copyright with all persons who have been involved in the production process of the
                  work and have obtained their agreement that the undersigned are the only authors
                  of the work.</p>
            </item>
            <item n="F" xml:id="s-d1e860" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Teaching Supplies and Photocopying</hi>
               <p>Effective October 1, 2015, the parties agree that the University of Lethbridge
                  will provide teaching supplies and photocopying for the purpose of teaching
                  University of Lethbridge courses at no cost to the Sessional Lecturer, consistent
                  with the level of such support provided to other ULFA Members covered under the
                  Faculty Handbook.</p>
            </item>
            <item n="G" xml:id="s-d1e994" ana="schedule">
               <hi rend="bold">Conclusion of Bargaining 2015 Sessional Lecturers Handbook</hi>
               <p>The parties hereby agree to recommend the following package to their principals
                  and commit to completing the ratification process before November 1, 2015.</p>
               <p>The effective date for this agreement is September 1, 2015 unless specifically
                  stated otherwise.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="G.01" xml:id="s-d1e1030">The term of the agreement is three years:<list>
                        <item n="G.01.1" xml:id="s-d1e1033">Year One: May 1, 2015 – April 30,
                           2016</item>
                        <item n="G.01.2" xml:id="s-d1e1035">Year Two: May 1, 2016 to April 30,
                           2017</item>
                        <item n="G.01.3" xml:id="s-d1e1037">Year Three: May 1, 2017 to April 30,
                           2018 </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="G.02" xml:id="s-d1e1040">Retroactive pay in Year One of the agreement
                     will be applied in the following manner:<list>
                        <item n="G.02.1" xml:id="s-d1e1043">An increase to the minimum stipend is
                           retroactive to September 1, 2015. </item>
                        <item n="G.02.2" xml:id="s-d1e1045">The following Sessional Lecturers are
                           eligible for retroactive pay:<list>
                              <item n="G.02.2.A" xml:id="s-d1e1048">Receives a stipend as of
                                 September 1, 2015 or later, AND</item>
                              <item n="G.02.2.B" xml:id="s-d1e1050">Remains as a Sessional Lecturer
                                 as of October 1, 2015 AND</item>
                              <item n="G.02.2.C" xml:id="s-d1e1052">Receives a stipend of less than
                                 $6000 per course as of September 1, 2015.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item n="G.02.3" xml:id="s-d1e1054">There is no retroactive application of
                           the minimum stipend for the period of May 1, 2015 to August 31, 2015, nor
                           for Sessional Lecturers who terminated their appointment on or before
                           October 1, 2015.</item>
                        <item n="G.02.4" xml:id="s-d1e1056">Retroactive pay will be applied by
                           December 2015 pay. </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item n="G.03" xml:id="s-d1e1059">The parties further agree to modify the
                     following Schedules in the July 1, 2014 Sessional Lecturers Handbook as
                     indicated in the attachments:<list>
                        <item n="G.03.1" xml:id="s-d1e1062">Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e806">A.01</ref>- Minimum Sessional Lecturer Stipend</item>
                        <item n="G.03.2" xml:id="s-d1e1064">Schedule <ref target="#s-d1e813">E</ref>
                           – Teaching Supplies and Photocopying.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
